The U.S.A.
美国
Richest nation on earth.
世界上最富有的国家
Hard work and ingenuity
我们付出了多少的努力和才智
earned us that title.
才赢得了这个称号
But we also got lucky.
但我们也足够幸运
This country has natural resources to spare.
这个国家拥有富饶的自然资源
How they came to be here is an ancient story,
它们的由来是个古老
and an unbelievably violent one.
而又无比暴烈的故事
探索频道
绝  对  好  奇
美国国土资源
I'm in California
我现在在加利福尼亚州
where we get an occasional jolt to remind us
偶尔的一次地震告诉我们
that this country is not built on solid ground.
这个国家并非建立在坚固的土地上
Down there under my feet,
我脚下的土地里
there's a fiery world of chaos,explosions,
隐藏着一个充满混乱  爆炸
collisions, contortions, upheaval
碰撞  挤压和剧变的世界
all on a scale we can hardly imagine.
所有的一切我们都难以想象
How did the extreme subterranean forces
这些极强的地下力量
and cataclysmic climatic events above ground
和地上的灾难性气候
shake the Continent?
是如何塑造这片大陆的
How did grinding sheets of ice miles thick
这些厚达几英里[几千米]的冰层
flatten the middle of the country?
是怎样覆盖美国中部的
What great pressures belched metals
是怎样巨大的压力使金属物质
to the surface from below?
冲破地表的
How are entire mountain ranges
山脉是怎样由巨大的地球板块
thrust up by colliding tectonic plates?
碰撞而形成
And how did all that violence give us the raw materials
而这些剧烈活动是怎样提供我们原材料
to ultimately build this land of power and bounty?
来创造这片富饶而又生机勃勃的土地的
Because it did just that.
它就是这样做到了
It built our cities,our rich farmland,
它建造了我们的城市  肥沃的农田
our waterways, our factories
水道  工厂
and lots of the things they make.
还有很多人工建筑
We're going to take you across America
我们会带领你横跨美国大陆
from the newest land here in the Pacific
从这儿  太平洋沿岸最新陆地出发
to some of the oldest land near the Great Lakes
经过一些五大湖地区的最老陆地
and along the Atlantic seaboard.
最后来到大西洋沿岸
We're going to find out
我们要找寻
just how this country's savage geological past
过去残酷的地质活动是怎样使这片土地
made it great.
变得如此美丽
First stop, Hawaii,
第一站  夏威夷
where the same geological forces that created America
创造美洲大陆的地质作用力
are still bubbling and exploding today.
仍在这里着发挥作用
They're building the most dangerous volcano in America.
它创造了美国最危险的火山
This 14,000 foot mountain
这个高达1.4万英尺[4267米]的火山
is constantly growing.
仍在生长
Molded by forces that shaped and reshaped the earth
45亿年来  创造它的作用力
over the last four and a half billion years.
也不断塑造并改造着地球
As heat rises up from deep inside the earth,
由地球深处传递出来的热量
it melts rock and blasts it through the crust.
将岩石熔为岩浆喷出地壳
When it cools,it hardens into a black basalt crust
冷凝后形成黑色的玄武石
that builds up over time,layer upon layer.
随时间推移层层叠加
It has created almost a thousand acres of new land
不到半个世纪  就这样形成了
in less than a half century.
近1000英亩[404公顷]的新陆地
Two and a half thousand miles to the east
在其东面2500英里[4023公里]处
on the mainland is much older land,
美国本土是更古老的大陆
long,dormant volcanoes have left golden riches
休眠火山带来的丰富的金矿
buried in the California rocks.
隐藏在加州的岩石下
California is the richest state in the U.S.,
加利福尼亚州是美国资源最丰富的州
and its good fortune began with its gold.
它的好运都源自它的金矿资源
Todd Bracken has been seeking and finding that gold for 20 years.
托德・布拉肯勘探金矿已经20年
托德・布拉肯  珠宝商
This is the most exciting part of my gold mining yet,
这是我采金中遇到最好的一块
this is a 43 gram natural California gold nugget.
重达43克的加利福尼亚天然金块
A nugget worth a cool  2,500.
一块金块的价值就高达2500美元
California's gold is as old as her hills.
加州的金子和她的山一样古老
It's been here over 100 million years.
已有超过1亿年的历史了
It was forced up to the surface
当整个大陆还在漂移的时候
when the entire continent was on the move.
它们就已经被顶出地表
California rests on top one of
加利福尼亚州位于
seven massive tectonic plates that make up the earth's crust.
组成地球地壳的七大板块之一之上
Blazing heat from the earth's core,up to 10,000 degrees
地核的高达1万度高温
keeps those plates in constant motion.
使地球板块不断移动
150 Million years ago,
1.5亿年前
the North American and Pacific Plates Collided.
北美板块和太平洋板块发生过碰撞
The force of that impact pushed up a chain of volcanoes
碰撞力顶起了
along what is now the west coast of the United States.
现在美国西海岸的火山带
And the Sierra Nevada Mountain Range was born.
内华达山脉随之诞生
This process had another effect.
这个过程带来了另一个影响
It seeded rocks throughout California with treasure.
使加利福尼亚州的岩层中布满矿藏
When tectonic plates smash into each other,
当地球板块相互碰撞时
things get hot,
温度升高
and turn solid rock into magma.
使岩石熔化成岩浆
Water,super heated by the magma
被岩浆加热的地下水
rip upward through the cracks in the California crust,
通过碰从裂缝里冲出加州地表
carrying gold from deep within the planet.
将金子从内部带到地球表面
When the liquid cooled,
金水冷却后
the gold solidified into flakes and nuggets
凝固成金片或金块
inside the quartz rich veins of the Sierra Nevada.
蕴藏在内华达山脉丰富的石英脉中
Good news for California and for this modern day prospector
这对加州和这位现代淘金者是个好消息
who is also a jeweler.
他也是一位珠宝商
Many people like the idea of buying my jewelry
很多人喜欢买我的首饰
because they know that
因为他们知道
it is mined right out of the ground here in California,
我的首饰都是刚从加州地下采上来的
and handmade right here in California.
并是在这儿纯手工打造的
Todd prospects for gold in the shadow of the original 49ers.
托德是49年淘金热的首批淘金者
The California Gold Rush lasted only 15 busy years.
加利福尼亚淘金热仅持续了15年
300,000 Prospectors from all over the world
来自全世界的30万淘金者
scooped up more than 70 million ounces.
淘出超过7千万盎司[1984吨]的金子
At today's prices,
以现在的金价来说
their total haul would be worth  130 billion.
总价值高达1300亿美元
California gold helped the union win the war.
加利福尼亚的金矿帮助国家赢得战争
赫斯特  美国报业巨头  创建赫斯特报系
It also founded the Hearst and Stanford Dynasties.
也造就了赫斯特和斯坦福的时代
So how exactly do you find the gold?
那到底是怎么发现金子的呢
The power of water erodes the rock,
水侵蚀岩石后
freeing the imbedded gold
嵌在岩石中的金子
and sweeping it downstream.
随着水流顺流而下
A boulder like this slows the river water down,
像这样的岩石减缓了河流的速度
creating a low pressure system behind it.
随之形成了低水压区
And when gravel fills in around it,
当碎石填满岩石周围的缝隙时
it sucks and holds the gold in behind boulders like that.
就会将金吸进并储存在岩石后
So this is the ideal situation to find gold.
所以这里是淘金的最佳地点
Two years ago
两年前
we found 16 ounces
六周就能挖出
in the course of about six weeks.
16盎司[453克]的金子
Six weeks of work.
六周的工作
A  27,000 pay day.
一天2.7万美元的报酬
Todd's prospecting methods haven't changed from
托德使用的淘金方法
those used by the 49ers.
还和49年的一样
This is gold panning.
这是在淘金
First,you pour the material into the pan
首先  你把你采到东西倒进淘盘中
and you give it quite a few shakes,
晃一晃
and what this does is
这么做是为了
settle the heavier gold down to the bottom of the pan.
使重的金子沉在盘底
If you pan it too fast,
如果你晃得太快
you run the risk of losing the gold.
很有可能会失掉金子
Gold.
金子
One, two, three.
一个  两个  三个
That's a nice piece.
这是块好金子
The geological forces that
将金矿带到内华达山脉的
shot gold into the Sierra Nevada's
地质作用力
gave America more than mineral riches,
带给美国的不仅是丰富的矿产资源
they built our magnificent landscapes,too.
还有壮丽的风景
800 Miles east
800亿年之后
and 80 million years later,
往东800英里[1287千米]的地方
they created the greatest mountain range in the U.S.
它创造了美国最大的山脉
For tens of millions of years,
数千万年来
the North American Plate
北美板块
continued to grind up and over the Pacific Plate.
与太平洋板块不断碰撞
That relentless force contorted and buckled the land,
作用力不断地挤压大陆
thrusting up the Rocky Mountains,5 miles into the sky.
隆起高达5英里[8046米]的落基山脉
The American Rockies run for 1,500 miles,
落基山脉全长1500英里[2414千米]
from Canada to New Mexico.
从加拿大延绵至新墨西哥州
To the east,they towered above
在其东面的平原
what would become the Powder River Basin in Wyoming.
之后演变成怀俄明州的粉河盆地
Now a dry prairie,
现在这片干燥的草原
this was once a feted swamp.
曾经也是富饶的沼泽
The surprising source of another one of America's natural treasures.
美国另一宝贵的自然财富
Coal.
煤
绝  对  好  奇
美国国土资源
This ever restless planet possesses awesome power.
这个永不停歇的星球拥有着巨大的能量
It can move mountains,
它可以移动山峦
divert the course of mighty rivers,
改变恢弘流川的方向
and transform millions of square miles of dry land
将数百万平方英里的干旱土地
into a vast,simmering swamp.
变成一片广阔而嘈杂的沼泽地
How did millions of years of rotting vegetation in just such a swamp
这片沼泽中 腐烂数百万年的植物
turn into America's most abundant source of fuel?
是如何转化成全美最丰富的燃料来源
Coal fuels half of the power stations in America.
煤炭是全美半数发电站的燃料
Almost half of all that coal
这些煤炭中几乎一半
comes from a single valley in Wyoming.
都来自怀俄明州的一片峡谷
The powder river basin.
粉河盆地
It covers over 20,000 square
绵延2万多平方英里[5万多平方公里]
miles of flat,dry prairie.
是一片平坦干燥的大草原
Coal from the powder river basin
来自粉河盆地的煤炭
yields enough electricity for
所产出的电力
one in five American homes.
足以供给全美五分之一的家庭使用
It is nice to be able to help
很高兴能为上百万人的
丹尼斯・罗格  铲车操作员
millions of people out in their daily life.
日常生活提供帮助
So they can see at night
让他们夜晚有光可见
alarm clocks can go off in the morning.
早上闹铃按时响起
They can fix their breakfast.
他们能够做早餐
Dennis Rogg operates a shovel
丹尼斯・罗格操作的铲车
that loads the mine's gargantuan trucks.
向矿区的巨型卡车中装煤
Each one holds 250 tons.
每辆卡车都能装载250吨
There's about 35 ton of coal in that bucket.
一铲斗大概有35吨煤
About seven bucket fulls in a truck.
七个铲斗才能填满一辆卡车
And it goes up in silos,through
卡车货斗升起
crushers into the silos,then
煤块经过碎煤机进入煤仓
they load it out on the trains from there.
然后从那儿装上火车
Lynn Huskinson drives one of
林恩・哈斯金森驾驶着
our largest loaders in America.
全美最大的装载机
It is as high as a two-story house.
足足有两层楼那么高
Actually the shovels are more efficient than the loader,
其实铲车比装载车的效率更高
but the loader can get into a tighter place
但是装载车可以开进更狭窄的地方
because it has articulation.
因为它有接合装置
Next step,you need a mile-long train
下一步  需要一列
to put the coal in.
1英里[1.6公里]长的火车来装载煤
Lots of coal.
很多很多煤
Like sometimes five,six,seven trains,
比如有时能装五六七列火车
110 coal cars.
110节载煤车厢
林恩・哈斯金森  装载车操作员
That's a good day I think.
那就是美好的一天
I love my job.
我热爱我的工作
I guess I have kind of taken it for granted,
一定程度上我觉得是理所当然的事
because this is something I've always done.
因为这是我一直在做的事情
I started when I was 19 years old.
我19岁就开始干了
I'm a native of Wyoming.
我是怀俄明州本地人
It's a beautiful state.
这是个美丽的州
Coal was created here.
这里的煤炭形成于
55 million years ago.
5500万年以前
Back then,this place looked very different.
那时候  这个地方面貌完全不一样
It was a giant bowl,surrounded
它像一只巨碗
on all sides by mountains.
被四周的群山环绕
The climate was radically different then,too.
那时的气候也完全不同
Subtropical, like Florida.
亚热带气候  像弗罗里达州
Warm and wet.
温暖而湿润
Rivers draining the newly formed.
从新形成的落基山脉上奔流而下的河川
Rockies drowned the land.
淹没了土地
The basin filled up and
盆地被填充沉积
it turned into a swamp,teaming with life.
变成一片生机勃勃的沼泽地
You won't find them in Wyoming today,
在今天的俄怀明州你已难寻它们踪迹
but back then,there were
但那时候  这里有
alligators, flamingos, and the
短吻鳄  火烈鸟
ancestors of today's redwood trees.
以及今日红杉树的祖先
When trees and plants die and
树木植被死去之后
fall into a swamp,they can't
沉入沼泽中
decompose,and instead turn into peat.
它们无法被分解  而是变成泥煤
Over millions of years,
经过数百万年的时间
the peat compacts to form coal.
泥煤日渐紧实形成煤
This piece of coal that I picked up here
我在这边捡起的这片煤
大卫・奥尔森  矿井地质学家
actually is has a piece of ambrite in it,
里面其实有一片灰黄琥珀
which is fossilized tree resin.
也就是树脂化石
About one foot of coal takes about 7 to 10
形成一英尺[0.3米]厚的煤大概需要
feet of peat to do that.
7-10英尺[2-3米]厚的泥煤
We have approximately 100 feet of coal here
这儿的煤约有100英尺[30米]高
that derive from that peat
都是那么多年
that accumulated in the swamp over those years.
沼泽地里沉积的泥煤转化而成的
And this whole deposit the Powder River Basin
这整片粉河盆地的煤储藏量
there's billions of tons of coal.
可达数十亿吨
Blasting is an easy way to
这些异常浅的煤箱
get at these unusually shallow coal bins.
可以通过炸药轻松开采
They cover an area twice the
它们的面积
size of New Jersey.
有两个新泽西州那么大
A legacy from the earth that
这份来自大地的遗产
keeps America's lights on and
让全美灯火通明
appliances and computers humming.
也让电器电脑得以运行
Enough here for at least another 100 years.
并且足以继续供给至少100年
And that's not the only fuel we've got under our American feet.
而且这还不是我们美国脚下唯一的燃料
We've also got
我们还有
oil.
石油
From Alaska to Texas,
从阿拉斯加州一直到德克萨斯州
California to Pennsylvania.
从加利福尼亚州绵延至宾夕法尼亚州
But this time the raw ingredients for the fuel
但这种燃料的原材料
were not dead plants,but dead animals.
不是死去的植物  而是死去的动物
360 Million years ago,
3.6亿年前
three-quarters of the American.
四分之三的美洲大陆
Continent was under a shallow sea.
都在一片浅海之下
The ancient sea swarmed with life.
原始海洋里充满着生命
As trillions of these sea creatures died,
随着数万亿海洋生物的死亡
their remains build up as thick organic sludge
它们的遗骸变成厚厚的有机淤泥
on the seabed.
仍然留在海床上
When the sludge was buried by
这些淤泥被一层层沉积物掩埋
layers of sediment and pressure-cooked
再经过地球内部数百万年的
for millions of years inside the earth,
高压"蒸煮"
it was transformed into oil.
淤泥就转化成了石油
Heading further east,
继续向东行进
we reach the fastest growing oil region in the U.S.
我们到达了美国发展最迅速的油区
North Dakota.
北达科他州
Here at the Bakken Oil Field,
在这个巴肯油田上
there are 5400 wells,
共有5400口油井
each with around 100 workers.
每口井都有约100名工人
I think it is great,
我觉得这活儿很棒
putting American citizens to work.
可以让所有美国公民正常工作
德里克・丹尼森  钻井技师
It is millions of people that
有几百万人都依靠
are having jobs from this,and
石油开展他们的工作
doing our economy great.
这我们的经济发展得很好
Derek has worked on oil rigs for the last 20 years.
丹尼森已在石油钻塔上工作20年了
Once you get mud in your blood,
一旦让泥浆进入你血液
it just doesn't come out.
就再也离不开了
Hopefully I get to teach my
希望能有机会
children this trade and they
教我的孩子们从事这个职业
enjoy it as much as I do.
也希望他们像我一样热爱这份工作
The oil here is trapped
这里的石油都蕴藏在
inside porous rock that's more than two miles deep.
超过两英里[三千多米]深的多孔岩中
When the drill penetrates the oil-rich layers
当钻头钻进富油层
the rock is shattered by small explosions
一次次小爆炸把石块粉碎
and oil is forced up to the surface.
石油便冲出地表
With such heavy and dangerous equipment,
要操作如此沉重而危险的器械
teamwork helps keep the men safe.
工人需要协作一致以保证安全
Best part of the job is
这份工作最美妙之处
the people you work with.
在于和你一同工作的人
Everybody on a rig is important
钻塔上每一个人都很重要
because no matter what,if that
因为无论如何
贾斯汀・迪  钻工
one person makes a mistake,
一旦其中一人犯错
it could jeopardize somebody's life
就可能危及钻塔上
somewhere else on the rig.
其他地方其他人的生命
Anything there gets loose,if
随便一松动
it hits you,it's gonna hurt.
就可能打到你  让你受伤
Depending on the size,
要看器械大小
may permanently injure you,may kill You.
小则留下永久创伤  大则要你小命
The oil reserves beneath North Dakota
北达科他州地下的石油储量
will keep these guys in work for at least 50 years.
可以保证这些人至少继续工作50年
It really makes you feel good
干完一天的活回到家
going home at the end of the day,
感觉很开心
and knowing that you've done something good for your country,
因为知道自己为国家做了些事
and trying to supply for them and
努力为国家输送能源
a good day's work.
并且干了一天整天的活
Oil is turned into a vast range of products,
石油可以制成一系列产品
none more essential than gas for our cars.
最重要的是为车辆提供汽油
American cars and trucks swallow.
全美的小汽车和卡车每天都要
378 million gallons of gas a day.
吞下3.78亿加仑[17亿升]的汽油
That's more than a gallon for each American citizen.
全美公民人均消耗超过1加仑[4.5升]
Every man,woman,and child.
算上每个男人  女人  小孩
Gold, oil, and coal.
黄金  石油  以及煤
All valuable natural resources
都是蕴藏在美国地下的
that lie beneath America.
珍贵自然资源
As our eastward trip continues,
随着我们东进之行的继续
we'll find another lucky break.
我们将发现另一种自然馈赠
The super fertile soil of the mid-west.
中西部的超级沃土
Midwest,where this nation of
农民们在中西部开疆僻壤
farmers found the perfect land.
找到了一片完美的沃土
绝  对  好  奇
美国国土资源
Stretching from Kansas to
从堪萨斯到达科他
the Dakotas,Iowa to Ohio is
从爱荷华到俄亥俄
what's called the fruited plain
这片疆域被称为
in America the beautiful.
美利坚沃土平原
The nation's bread basket.
是这个国家的产粮区
Kevin Ames farms his Ilinois
凯文・埃姆斯像他父亲和祖父那样
land like his father and grandfather before him.
耕耘着他在伊利诺伊州的土地
Well,it's interesting living
远离喧嚣  以农耕为生
凯文・埃姆斯 农民
out here and farming for a living.
其实是很惬意的
My family has been doing it over a hundred years.
我的家族一百多年来一直以此为生
There is great abundance here.
这里资源丰富
The fine-grain prairie soil
细腻的草原土壤
is perfect for wheat,corn,and soy beans.
很适合小麦  玉米和大豆的生长
Well,this soil is very highly productive.
这里的土地很高产
It's a silty clay-loam soil.
属于砂质黏壤土
It's probably five or six
大概有百分之五到六的
percent organic matter.
有机物含量
Has great water-holding ability.
持水能力特别强
This soil is very dark
这是一片黑土大地
and just grows great crops
农作物茁壮生长
to help feed illinois and the world.
哺育着伊利诺伊州乃至全世界
There's a two-million-year-old
这片富饶的土地的背后
secret behind the richness of this soil.
隐藏着一个两百万年之久的秘密
Right around then,the Great Ice Age arrived.
那个时候正赶上大冰期时代
85% Of the area we now call the
我们现在所说的中西部地区
midwest was cloaked in ice.
在那时有百分之八十五被冰雪覆盖
Glaciers up to a mile high moved
厚达一英里[一点六公里]的冰川
relentlessly across the land.
无情的穿过大陆
They ripped up rock and
它们粉碎了岩石
pulverized anything that stood in their way.
沿途一路碾压过去
This bulldozing effect ground
这种推土机式的前进
the rock into dust.
化巨石为尘土
Almost two million years later
直到两百万年后
when the ice sheets finally retreated,
冰川终于退去
they exposed what they crushed.
被它们碾过的地方得以重见天日
Rock dust,rich in minerals,
富含矿物质的岩石尘埃
was blown across the land.
撒落在大地上
And that's why the midwestern
所以如今美国中西部的土壤
soil is so very fertile.
才得以如此的肥沃
We had several glaciers come through this area
得益于几条穿过这里的冰川
that helped level the soil,
使得土地变得平坦
and grind the stones into soil.
把石头磨碎并混入土壤
The giant glaciers had a further beneficial effect.
巨型冰川带来的好处远不止于此
The heavy ice flattened and leveled the landscape.
沉重的冰川让地表也变得平整
To work these flat expanses,
为了在这片平原上开疆拓土
American ingenuity created mega machines.
美国人靠着聪明才智发明了大型农业机械
This increased productivity by leaps and bounds
为生产力带来了质的飞跃
to feed our ever growing population.
满足了日益增长的人口数量的需要
I think as a farmer,
作为一个农民
a lot of times we take the land for granted,
我总觉得靠地吃饭是理所应当的
but we're very fortunate
但其实能够生活在这个国家
to live in this rich,
最为富饶肥沃的土地上
fertile part of the country.
是何等的幸运的事
It's something that is a blessing.
这是上帝的恩赐
The legacy of the Great Ice Age
大冰期年代不光留下了
didn't end with these flat,fertile fields.
这些平坦而富饶的土地
When the glaciers melted,
当冰川融化时
they unleashed billions of gallons of Water.
它们还释放出数十亿加仑的水
It surged across the land.
生成的激流在大地上奔腾而过
The torrents rerouted ancient Rivers,
激流改变了古代河流的走向
eventually creating one mighty river.
最终融汇成一条浩荡的大河
The Mississippi.
密西西比河
Today,it's a critical commercial thoroughfare.
今天  它是一条十分重要的商业航道
The Mississippi connects the agricultural,
密西西比河把工农业发达
industrial,and resource rich northern
且资源丰富的美国中北部
and central states to the gulf of mexico.
和墨西哥湾连接了起来
Water from 31 states flows into this river.
来自三十一个州的河流都汇集于此
Its million-square-mile watershed
密西西比河数百万英里的流域
drains 40% of the U.S.
占据了全美河流总和的百分之四十
30,000 Barges work the river.
三万多艘货船在河里营运
Each year,they transport more
它们每年要运载超过
than  20 billion of American goods and commodities.
两百亿的商品和货物
Steel,cement,coal,and wheat.
钢铁  水泥  煤炭和小麦
Products going all over the World.
这些产品被运往世界各地
大卫・穆思尔  水手
It's good for America,you know.
这对美国是好事
If it comes out of america
如果这些产品出口美国
and it goes somewhere else,
并远销海外的话
then it's good for America,
美国将受益
and I'm all for that.
我很支持
Longer than the ill fated.
每艘货船从船首到船尾
Titanic and more than a little tricky to navigate,
长有一千英尺[二百五十米]还要多
Each barge stretches 1,000 feet
比命运坎坷的泰坦尼克还要长
or more from bow to stern.
也更难驾驭
For twenty eight days straight
在二十八天的航程中
the barges are home sweet home
这货船对船上的工人来说
to the men that work them.
如同一个幸福甜蜜的家
Our boat is like -- it's a pride thing,you know.
我为我们的船而自豪
弗吉尼亚・英格拉姆号船员
We take care of each other.
我们互相关心
Actually,as we love each other.
我们亲如兄弟
Yeah, a family thing.
像是一家人
We eat at the dinner table together,
我们在一张桌子吃饭
spend Christmas together,Thanksgivings together.
一起过圣诞节和感恩节
It is a lifestyle.
这是一种生活方式
I love it right now.
我乐在其中
You see pleasure boats,
其他游艇经过时
people waving,we wave back.
对方挥手致意  我们挥手回礼
August this year will be.
到今年八月为止
13 Years that I been on the river.
我就在这条河上干了整整十三年了
Right now,the crew of the virginia Ingram
现在  弗吉尼亚・英格拉姆号的船员
is navigating the upper reaches of the.
正在位于密苏里州圣路易斯市
Mississippi,north of st.Louis,Missouri.
北边的密西西比河上游航行
A fully laden barge like this
这样一艘满载的货船
needs an 18-man crew.
需要十八名船员
We're the eyes and ears of the pilot,you know.
我们就是舵手的眼睛和耳朵
He can't see where he's at,
他看不到具体的位置
especially these covered tops,
特别是这些被货物挡住的死角
they can't see the corners.
他们还看不见转弯处
The lock is 110 wide,
水闸110英尺[28米]宽
and tow is 105 wide.
拖船105英尺[26米]宽
So what I see are relate to him on the radio.
我用无线电和他汇报情况
He has to trust me.
他必须相信我
If he don't trust me,you have catastrophe.
如果他不相信我  就有可能出大事
We're a little cog in a big wheel,but,you know,
我们虽然只是个机器上的小零件
We try to do our best,work safely,
但一样要竭尽全力  保证工作安全
and keep things going like they should.
让一切正常运转
Navigating the river on a
驾驶这么大一条货船
mega barge takes enormous skill.
在河上航行必须技术纯熟
In 1996,
在1996年
a barge this size lost its steering
一艘同样大小的货船曾失去了控制
and demolished a riverside shopping mall.
撞毁了河边的一座商场
Pushed a lot of tonnage.
这次载了很多吨的货物
We've got about 28,000 tons that
我们需要把这两万八千吨货物
we're shoving up through the river system.
运送并穿过河道航行系统
And right now,
目前为止
唐・迈克丹尼尔  船长
probably about 1,000 feet to stop.
还有1000英尺[250米]就到岸了
I like my job.
我热爱我的工作
I like being around the water for some reason.
我就是喜欢在河边呆着
I don't know,
不知何故
I always liked it since I was a kid,
我打小就喜欢
being around Water.
在河边呆着
It is a cheap means of transportation.
这也算是一种交通运输系统吧
It is what helped build this country.
为建设国家添砖加瓦
When these cargos reach their destination,
这些货物一旦到达目的地
they're offloaded,bound for other parts of the U.S.
就被卸下船  随即运往美国其他地区
And the rest of the world.
乃至世界各地
All made possible by melting glaciers.
冰川消融让这一切变得可能
Off the river and heading east again,
离岸后继续向东航行
the next stop is michigan.
下一站密西根州
It's a state endowed with what
这里盛产被誉为整个美国
is arguably America's greatest natural resource.
无可争议的最伟大的自然资源
Iron.
铁
Michigan's iron drove America's industrial revolution
密西根的铁矿主宰了美国的工业革命
and literally built modern America.
打造了一个真正现代化的美国
绝  对  好  奇
美国国土资源
America has a backbone of solid steel.
美国的支柱就是坚韧的钢材
It's built our bridges,
它被用来建造桥梁
railroads, ships, tanks,
铁路  船舶  坦克
factories, cars, and aircraft.
工厂  汽车还有飞机
For centuries,
几个世纪以来
we have dug,carved,blasted
我们通过挖掘  开采  爆破
great bands of iron ore out of the ground.
得到了大量的铁矿石
But what made American iron so accessible and
是什么让美国的铁矿石如此容易开采
how did it get there in the first place?
而当初它又是怎么被埋入地下的呢
The story of america's iron
关于美国的铁矿的故事
begins 11 billion years ago.
始于110亿年前
Earth did not exist.
那时还没有地球
But iron rich dust left behind
但是上古星球的爆炸
from an ancient exploding star
遗留了富含铁元素的尘埃
began to circle and collide in space.
它们逐渐在宇宙中周转并相撞
Five and a half billion years later,
55亿年后
our planet was formed.
我们的地球形成了
Heavy elements,which included most of the iron,
重元素  包括大部分的铁元素
sank to form the Earth's molten core.
沉入形成熔融的地核
But some iron remained topside,
但有些铁还残留在上层
trapped in rock in the crust of the ancient planet.
蕴藏在这个古老星球的地壳岩石中
A rich concentration of these rocks is here
这些富饶的岩层集中在
in Michigan's upper peninsula.
在密歇根州上半岛地区
Michigan mines produce a quarter of America's iron ore.
美国四分之一的铁矿都从密歇根矿山开采
Driving down the road in an active mine,
沿着正在开采的矿山一路开下去
艾尔・斯特兰莱 矿物学家
so a lot of the rocks in this area
这片地区的很多岩层
have already been extracted out.
已经被采掘过
Like our underground stores of oil,
正如我们地下存储的原油
the iron deposits here date back to
沉积在这里的铁  要追溯到
when much of our continent was covered in water.
很多大陆还在水下的时期
You would have to go 1.85 billion years.
你得回到18亿5千万年前
At that time,there would have been a shallow sea in this area.
那时候  这里还是片浅海
So we would be under water right now.
所以现在我们应该在水下
The ancient sea ebbed and flowed for a billion years.
远古海洋潮起潮落了十亿年
Over that time,iron from deeper in the Earth's crust
在此期间  地壳深处的铁
came up through cracks in the sea bed,carried by super-heated steam.
随着过热蒸汽从海床的裂缝中析出
The iron particles sank and settled on the ocean floor,
铁粒子沉积在海底
mixed between layers of sand.
混合在砂层之间
These are the red banded iron deposits
这些红色带状铁矿沉积层
found in this Michigan mine today.
现如今被发现在这片密歇根矿区中
We know from exploration drilling
我们知道从钻孔勘探来看
that we have at least 3,000 feet
连续的含铁地质层
of continuous iron formation.
至少3000英尺[914米]深
And in most of the areas here,
实际上  这里的大部分区域
we actually have not drilled down
我们还没下钻到
to the bottom of that iron formation yet.
那些含铁层的底部
What we got right here is the banded iron formation.
现在这些就是条带状含铁层
It is a lot harder.
它们要坚硬的多
It wears our bits out,
会磨损钻头
takes longer to drill.
使钻探时间更长
The numbers tells us how deep we are in the hole,
这些数量告诉我们洞中的深度
杰夫・比尔斯  钻工
so we don't lose track of what depth we're at.
这样我们就不会忘记所在地的深度
This is Dearborn, Michigan.
这里是密歇根州  迪尔伯恩
The site of Henry Ford's original steel plant.
亨利・福特的第一家炼钢厂所在地
Here iron mined from the banded iron ore
在这里  从带状铁矿里开采的铁矿石
is transformed into steel.
被冶炼成钢铁
24 Automobiles can be made from one single slab of this steel.
一块钢板可以制作24辆汽车
Turning iron into steel is not for the faint-hearted.
将铁炼成钢需要胆量
Carbon and other elements need to be added at extreme temperatures--
碳和其他元素需要在极端温度下加入冶炼
up to 3,500 degrees--
高达3500摄氏度
seven times hotter than a home oven.
温度是家用烤箱的7倍
That's why we wear aluminized jackets,
那就是为什么我们要穿镀铝外套
塞德里克・威廉姆斯  铸造车间主管
shrouds, spats.
戴护罩和护脚
Lt can be pretty frightening at times,
有时候令人非常恐惧
because we have sparks shooting at you,
因为火花会射向你
sometimes you may get a drop of iron coming your way.
有时会有一滴铁水溅在你身上
You have to really pay attention to what you're doing.
工作时必须集中注意力
Nothing to play with.
要心无旁骛
Iron is one of Earth's heaviest metals.
铁是地球上最重的金属之一
It's so heavy,
它非常重
it sinks to the bottom of the furnace,
能沉到熔炉的底部
leaving the impurities which are lighter behind.
留下较轻的杂质
We have a lot of pressure on the furnace,
熔炉内压力很高
and the iron is heavy.
铁很重
And so when you open the hole,
所以当你打开炉门
iron is the first thing that comes out.
铁是第一个流出来的
More than 11 billion years after its creation,
在铁产生一百一十多亿年后
the iron is returned to its liquid state.
它重回到了液态
Then the workers add metal alloys to produce steel,
接下来工人们加入合金来生产钢铁
which is much stronger and more malleable than pure iron.
它的硬度和延展性要比纯铁好得多
I feel very fortunate that America has given us
我觉得非常幸运  美国用来冶钢的
斯蒂芬・戈登  船舶经营人
all the great resources of iron to make steel,
所有铁矿资源各方面都超乎寻常得好
so we can give them to the rest of the world.
这样我们就能把钢铁卖给全世界
Henry Ford started this a hundred years ago.
亨利・福特一百年前开创钢铁产业
We still have some of the original building.
我们仍然保留了一些当年的建筑
I have great pride to be able to work in this place
能在亨利・福特创业的地方工作
that Henry Ford started.
我非常自豪
From the iron ore beneath our feet,
从我们脚下的铁矿
American steel has found its way
美国的钢铁通过制造加工
into millions of automobiles.
转变成了数百万辆汽车
Iron has been used to make everything
铁被用来制造一切
from skyscraper girders to fire hydrants.
从摩天大楼的主梁到消防栓
Actually,it's kind of funny.
实际上  这挺有意思的
We'll drive down the road,
我们沿路驱车直下时
and I know that we made a part for that vehicle
我知道那辆车的一部分是我们做的
or we made steel for that appliance,
或者那个器械所需的钢铁是我们炼的
and I can say that I was part of that.
我能说我是其中的一员
As we continue heading east,
随着我们继续向东
we come to a mountain range that,
来到一座山脉
like the Rockies,
例如落基山脉
stretches down the entire length of the continent.
延伸到整个大陆的长度
Only these mountains are much older
只有这些山脉形成时间更久远
and were much taller.
曾经更高耸
They were a critical factor
它们是最早期
in the success of the earliest European settlers.
欧洲移民成功的一个关键因素
The Appalachians.
阿巴拉契亚山脉
绝  对  好  奇
美国国土资源
America,the most powerful land on Earth.
美国  地球上最有影响力的国家
Solid as a rock,right?
坚如磐石  对吗
Wrong.
你错了
Go back a few hundred million years,
回溯几亿年前
and this continent was being battered,bent
这片大陆被各种难以想象力量
and shunted around by forces almost impossible to imagine.
猛击  弯曲  撕扯
What knocked our continent into
是什么东西和我们的大陆相撞
the shape we know today
成为现如今这个类型
and created the oldest mountains we have?
并且创造出最古老的山脉呢
It all happened 300 million years ago
这全都发生在三亿年前
when the ancient continents of Europe and North Africa
当远古欧洲和北非洲大陆
smashed into the forerunner of North America...
猛撞在北美洲大陆的尖端上
And formed a new super continent -- Pangaea.
形成了一个新的超级大陆  盘古大陆
The impact was even greater than the geological collision
那次撞击比形成罗基山脉的地质碰撞
that formed the Rockies.
还要猛烈
It forced up one of the tallest mountain ranges
它曾经使最高山脉之一
that has ever been,
平地而起
although you wouldn't know it today.
虽然现在你们可能未曾耳闻
The ground here is still moving,
这里的土地仍然在运动
shifting along fault lines left over
从原始碰撞
from that primeval collision...
沿着断层线转移残留
and occasionally creating earthquakes,
有时会引起地震
like the one in Virginia,
例如2011年8月弗吉尼亚州地震
felt over much of the eastern U.S.In August,2011.
美国东部大部分有震感
When they were first formed,
在它们形成初期
the Appalachians were jagged and higher
比起喜马拉雅山脉
than the Himalayas.
阿巴拉契亚山脉更加高耸崎岖
Like all old mountains,
正如所有古老的山脉一样
they have eroded down to gentler slopes,
它们被侵蚀之后形成了较低缓的山坡
little more than hills
比丘陵稍高些
running 2,000 miles
从阿拉巴马州至加拿大
from Alabama to Canada.
绵延2000英里[3219千米]
They may be old,
它们可能年代久远
but they still yield natural riches.
但仍有丰富的自然资源
The northern end of the range
山脉的北部末端
dominates the interior of Maine.
占据了缅因州内部
Here, the worn-down mountains
在这里低缓的山脉
are shrouded in 17 million acres of forest.
被1700万亩[113亿平方米]森林覆盖
Trees cover 80% of the state.
覆盖了该州百分之八十的面积
Dick Slike manages the forest.
迪克・斯莱克管理森林
If you look at the state of Maine
你如果看着缅因州
and think of its geologic history,
想到其地质史
of course,the mountains were built ages ago.
当然  山脉很久以前就形成了
They're ancient,ancient mountains,
它们是很古老  很古老的山脉
迪克・斯莱克  木材公司经理
and the bedrock is granite.
基岩是花岗岩
Over time, that rock
久而久之  那块岩石
that rock has eroded
基岩渐渐被侵蚀
and donated its valuable minerals to the forest soil.
并为森林土壤贡献出珍贵的矿物质
And,of course,then you have the trees dropping the leaves,
当然  树上的叶子也会落下来
which becomes humus.
成为腐植质
And so the soil becomes a thin layer of inorganic soil
于是土壤变成薄薄的一层无机土壤
topped by a thick layer of leaves and needles
上面覆盖着厚厚一层叶子和松针
and things that become an organic component.
以及其他东西  成为有机成分
Maine's logging industry is worth  4 billion a year,
缅因州的伐木业每年产值40亿美元
and it has been important economically for hundreds of years.
而几百年来  它的经济地位都很重要
My father was a logger.
我的父亲是个伐木工人
戴尔・巴切尔德  设备操作工
His father before him was a logger.
我父亲的父亲是个伐木工人
我父亲的父亲的父亲也是伐木工人
They basically started logging
他们从苏格兰和英格兰来这里后
when they came over here from Scotland and England,
便开始了伐木的工作
so it goes back a long ways.
所以这份工作历史悠久
The forests that grow on the Appalachian slopes
贯穿美国东部的阿帕拉契亚山脉上的森林
up and down the eastern U.S.Were a vital resource
对印第安人和欧洲来的早期移民来说
for both Native Americans and early settlers from Europe.
都是极为重要的资源
I think when people came across on the wooden ships,
我认为当人们乘坐木船来到这里时
instantly people that had worked wood in Scandinavia or Europe
在斯堪的纳维亚和欧洲与木头打交道的人
saw the potential.
立即看到了潜在的可能性
They built their homes out of the wood.
他们用木头建造了自己的家
It was a basic building block that got people started.
这是促使人们开始伐木的基本要素
The first Europeans arrived in Maine in 1609.
1609年  首批欧州移民抵达缅因州
The Appalachian forest gave them
阿帕拉契亚的森林
not only the means to survive,
不仅给他们提供了生存途径
but to expand.
更扩大了生存的规模
[Sandian]Started to build,
他们开始建造房屋
they took the trees down all over the state of Maine,
他们把缅因州的树木砍倒
pushed them down the rivers to Bangor and those places,
顺着河流推下去  漂到班戈之类的地方
sawed them into boards,
把它们锯成木板
and basically built America with those boards.
基本上是用那些木板建造了整个美国
Boards from Appalachian timber are still used
用阿帕拉契亚的木材做的木板仍然在用于
to build American homes,churches,and railroad ties.
建造美国的家庭住宅  教堂和铁路轨枕
And Maine's logging industry supports more than 50,000 jobs.
缅因州的伐木业提供超过五万个工作岗位
I honestly believe that you couldn't live without logging
我真心觉得  伐木是生存必须
because you basically build your houses out of it,
因为你得用木头来盖房子
a lot of people keep warm by it,and it's real important.
很多人用木头取暖  这真的很重要
I think the forests of Maine will definitely help give America
我认为缅因州的森林一定会帮助美国
its future and its shape.
塑造它的未来
There's always going to be vast forest production here.
这里一直都会有庞大的森林产业
Appalachian rock underpins more than just economic success.
阿巴拉契亚的岩石不仅支撑着经济成就
It's the solid platform that allowed New York City
也是为纽约市提供了坚实的平台
to reach for the sky.
直耸入云
绝  对  好  奇
美国国土资源
Along the Atlantic coast,
在大西洋海岸线上
mountains are so eroded
山体被严重侵蚀
that you would hardly know they're there.
你几乎感觉不到它们的存在
But the bedrock remains
但岩床留存了下来
and plays a surprisingly important role.
并意外地扮演重要角色
It gives a solid base for the skyscrapers of Manhattan.
它成为了曼哈顿的摩天大楼的坚实地基
The higher these buildings rise into the sky,
这些建筑越是耸入云霄
the more they have to be rooted into the earth beneath.
它们地底的地基就必须越坚实
This is ground zero,
这里是世贸中心遗址
site of the new World Trade Center -
也是新的世贸中心的建造地点
the biggest civil engineering project in America.
美国最大的建筑工程项目
Here,the hard,eroded bedrock of the Appalachians
在这里  阿帕拉契亚的坚硬的
will soon support seven soaring towers.
被侵蚀的岩床即将支撑七座高塔
The first - 52 stories high - has already been built.
其中第一座52层高的楼已经完工
Engineers have dug over 100 feet down
工程师们向古老的基岩深处
into the ancient bedrock.
挖掘了超过100英尺[30米]
Right now,we are about 74 feet below sea level.
现在我们大约在海平面下74英尺[23米]
安德鲁・波耐科沃  岩土工程师
So we're standing on a rock excavation,
我们正站在岩层开挖处
and the natural bedrock was probably 10 or 15 feet higher
而天然的岩床比我站的地方
than where I'm standing right now.
大概要高10到15英尺[3到4.6米]
It's actually a very hard rock.
实际上  这基岩非常坚固
It was originally soft,sedimentary rock
这原来是较软的沉积岩
and was transformed into hard,crystalline rock
然后在大陆碰撞时
when the continents collided.
转变为坚硬的晶质岩
The heat and the pressure changed the rock
高温和压力使岩石发生变化
from the original components
使它们从最初的组成结构
into this crystalline rock that we have now
转变为我们现在看到的晶质岩
that allows us to put these building loads on top of it.
从而使其能够承载我们的建筑负荷
There's no question there would have been a settlement here,
毫无疑问  这里一定可以成为定居点
and probably a city,
也许会是一座城市
but not this city -
但没有这天然平台建造高楼的话
not without its natural platform for building up.
就不是现在的纽约了
I grew up here,I live here,it's great.
我在这里成长  居住  这里很棒
斯科特・汤普森  建筑公司主管
But,you know,just think of the history of Manhattan,
但只要想想曼哈顿的历史
you know,it's where it all started.
这是一切开始的地方
America began,yeah,the pilgrims came to other parts,
美国历史的开端  清教徒来到其他地方
but they all came to New York
但他们之所以来到纽约
because it was a great place to build a city.
是因为这里是建造城市的绝佳地点
The hard bedrock meant that
坚硬的岩床意味着
some of the first-ever skyscrapers were built here.
一些最早的摩天大楼就是在这里建造的
And today,
如今
the city has the most famous skyscrapers in the world.
这座城市拥有全世界最著名的摩天大楼
You've got the Chrysler Building,
我们有克莱斯勒大厦
and then,of course,we've got the Empire State Building.
当然  我们还有帝国大厦
That's,you know,everyone thinks of New York,
当人们想到纽约时
they think of the Chrysler Building
他们会想到克莱斯勒大厦
and the Empire State Building.
和帝国大厦
They're all sitting on bedrock.
它们都建造在岩床上
But Manhattan's bedrock isn't totally flat.
但是曼哈顿的岩床并不完全平坦
In some places it curves downward,
在有些地方  基岩向下弯曲
and the depressions have been filled in
而这些洼地则被
with softer, younger rock.
更软的  更新的岩石填满
Under Greenwich Village,
在格林威治村的地下
a dip in the bedrock below is mirrored above ground
地底基岩的凹陷与地上天际线的凹陷
by a dip in the skyline.
是相互呼应的
In Midtown,where the bedrock is nearer the surface,
在市中心  基岩较接近地表之处
the skyscrapers reappear.
摩天大楼又重新出现
A 21st-century American city
一座在300万年前的地基上建造的
built upon foundations created 300 million years ago.
21世纪美国城市
When the Appalachians were thrown up,
当阿帕拉契亚山脉崛起时
they were the greatest mountains on Earth.
它们是地球上最雄伟的山脉
100 Million years later,
一亿年之后
the supercontinent,Pangaea,split apart.
超级大陆  盘古大陆分裂了
North America,
北美洲
in more or less the same shape we know it today,
大致与我们今天所知的形状一致
was born.
形成了
In our journey across America,
在我们环游美国的旅途中
we've found tremendous riches
我们发现了来自于我们脚下的
that have come from beneath our feet -
巨大的财富
volcanic outpourings of lava in our most western state...
我国最西部的州的火山喷涌的岩浆
gold that helped create California's wealth...
帮助创造了加州财富的金子
coal and oil from living plants and animals
由曾经在古老的海域和沼泽里
that once thrived in ancient seas and swamps...
繁荣一时的动植物演变而来的煤与石油
iron from which we have built our cars,bridges,and railroads...
我们用来制造汽车  桥梁和铁路的铁
timber to build our houses...
用来建造房屋的木材
and the rock foundations of our mighty skyscrapers.
以及我们非凡的摩天大楼的岩石地基
Over billions of years,the land that was to become the U.S.A.
几十亿年以来  美国所在的土地中
Was endowed with greater geological riches
蕴藏着的地质宝藏
than any other nation on Earth.
比地球上的任何其他国家都要多
It's taken centuries of invention,industry and skill
我们通过数个世纪的发明  工业和技术
for us to dig,blast,and tease those resources -
才从美国的地下
what lies beneath America - out of the ground.
挖掘出  炸出  抽出那些资源
Nature's raw power and the courage of the American people
大自然的原始威力与美国人民的勇气
have been the unstoppable forces
是使我们成为如今这个富饶强大的国家的
that made us the rich and powerful nation we are today.
势不可挡的力量
马田・辛 美国演员 曾出演《白宫群英》中 约书亚・巴特勒总统一角
M 115 64 l 115 35 l 171 0 l 177 0 l 133 46 l 143 52 l 179 0 l 184 0 l 159 63 l 229 107 l 229 182 l 145 96 l 135 122 l 207 227 l 137 227 l 115 172 l 115 93 l 126 76 l 115 64 l 104 76 l 115 93 l 115 172 l 93 227 l 23 227 l 95 122 l 84 96 l 0 182 l 0 107 l 70 63 l 45 0 l 50 0 l 87 52 l 97 46 l 52 0 l 59 0 l 115 35
m 71 60 b 71 0 161 0 161 60 b 161 120 71 120 71 60
m 325 0 l 355 0 l 332 47 l 354 47 l 399 136 l 369 136 l 328 53 l 288 136 l 257 136 l 325 0 m 467 0 l 497 0 l 474 47 l 496 47 l 541 136 l 511 136 l 470 53 l 430 136 l 399 136 l 467 0 m 545 1 l 583 1 l 583 14 l 568 14 l 568 19 l 583 19 l 583 30 l 568 30 l 568 34 l 599 34 l 599 30 l 583 30 l 583 19 l 599 19 l 599 14 l 583 14 l 583 1 l 611 1 b 616 1 622 6 622 10 l 622 36 l 652 0 l 678 0 l 644 41 l 622 41 l 622 47 l 596 47 l 597 54 l 625 54 l 625 68 l 541 68 l 541 54 l 572 54 l 571 47 l 545 47 l 545 1 m 583 72 l 583 85 l 569 85 l 569 90 l 598 90 l 598 85 l 583 85 l 583 72 l 611 72 b 615 72 621 78 621 82 l 653 44 l 678 44 l 644 86 l 621 86 l 621 103 l 597 103 l 597 136 l 570 136 l 564 126 l 562 136 l 542 136 l 548 107 l 568 107 l 565 121 l 571 121 l 571 103 l 547 103 l 547 72 l 583 72 m 600 107 l 620 107 l 624 124 l 653 89 l 679 89 l 642 136 l 615 136 l 618 132 l 606 132 l 600 107 m 689 0 l 716 0 l 721 15 l 732 15 l 732 30 l 718 56 l 731 56 l 735 100 l 721 100 l 717 59 l 714 64 l 714 136 l 693 136 l 693 79 l 676 79 l 707 30 l 679 30 l 679 15 l 694 15 l 689 0 m 738 0 l 804 0 b 807 0 813 6 813 9 l 813 87 l 794 87 l 794 14 l 756 14 l 756 87 l 763 77 l 763 21 l 787 21 l 787 91 l 798 91 l 798 120 l 820 120 l 812 136 l 778 136 l 778 90 l 748 136 l 723 136 l 756 87 l 738 87 l 738 0 m 257 151 l 275 151 l 297 182 l 319 151 l 337 151 l 304 197 l 304 227 l 290 227 l 290 197 l 257 151 m 337 151 l 355 151 l 377 182 l 399 151 l 417 151 l 384 197 l 384 227 l 370 227 l 370 197 l 337 151 m 425 192 l 447 192 b 445 181 427 181 425 192 l 410 192 b 414 162 458 162 462 192 l 462 206 l 425 206 b 425 210 429 212 433 213 l 462 213 l 462 227 l 433 227 b 412 227 408 203 410 192 m 462 151 l 532 151 l 532 165 l 504 165 l 504 227 l 489 227 l 489 165 l 462 165 l 462 151 m 580 172 l 580 186 l 549 186 b 543 186 543 192 549 192 l 565 192 b 589 192 589 227 565 227 l 532 227 l 532 213 l 565 213 b 570 213 570 206 565 206 l 549 206 b 524 206 524 172 549 172 l 580 172 m 592 213 l 606 213 l 606 227 l 592 227 l 592 213 m 639 172 l 665 172 l 665 186 l 639 186 b 623 186 623 213 639 213 l 665 213 l 665 227 l 639 227 b 603 227 603 172 639 172 m 700 184 b 722 184 722 215 700 215 l 700 229 b 740 229 740 170 700 170 b 660 170 660 229 700 229 l 700 215 b 680 215 680 184 700 184 m 737 172 l 782 172 b 803 172 813 177 813 198 l 813 228 l 799 228 l 799 198 b 799 186 793 187 782 187 l 782 228 l 768 228 l 768 187 l 752 187 l 752 228 l 737 228 l 737 172
YYeTs.com
人人影视
原创翻译  双语字幕
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为 更多影视更新 请登陆www.YYeTs.com
m 20 0 l 209 0 b 218 0 229 11 229 20 l 229 209 b 229 218 218 228 209 228 l 20 228 b 11 228 0 218 0 209 l 0 20 b 0 11 11 0 20 0
翻译：宝宝  芒果喵  令狐伟  幸田实果子  DawningZ
校对：麦结   总监： 麦结
后期：蜡笔小新的眉毛     时间轴：GY瓷糕